{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A paper by Donald Regan interprets the result of this court case to hold that people cannot be forced to become Good Samaritans. Justice Byron White claimed that the result of this case was the only irredeemable error the court made during his tenure. The Casey case built upon the result of this case to expand the definition of the word “viability,” doing away with its trimester-based framework. For ten points, name this 1973 case that legalized abortion in the U.S.",
      "answer": [
        "Roe v. Wade",
        "either underlined portion",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Shortly after reports of this scandal emerged, the Bybee Memo was leaked, which was followed shortly by the resignation of Jack Goldsmith. Antonio Taguba’s report on this scandal concluded that Brigadier General Janis Karpinski allowed it to continue. One picture that emerged from this scandal depicts Charles Graner and Lynnie England giving a thumbs up behind a naked human pyramid. For ten points, name this scandal regarding US military personnel torturing detainees of an Iraqi prison.",
      "answer": "Abu Ghraib prison torture scandal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Before this battle, Thomas Rusk was told to take control if another commander refused to fight. The “Twin Sister” cannons were smuggled down the Mississippi River in preparation for this battle. Manuel Castrillon’s sleeping troops were ambushed in this battle, in which the victorious side rallied with cries to “remember the Alamo.” During this 18-minute engagement, the troops of Sam Houston captured Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna. For ten points, name this battle that secured Texan independence from Mexico.",
      "answer": "Battle of San Jacinto"
    },
    {
      "question": "On this island, the ambush of the Four Four Bravo patrol prompted racial violence during Black July. Lourenco de Almeida established a Portuguese fort on this island to counter Jaffna influence. Thanks to the evangelizing of Mahinda, Ashoka’s son, Theravada Buddhism is prominent on this island, contrary to the neighboring mainland. For ten points, name this home island of the Sinhalese and Tamil ethnic groups, a country whose largest city is Colombo.",
      "answer": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "Ceylon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Bruce Hoffman’s “Inside [this activity]” describes the way in which it has been politicized by its victims. Alan Krueger’s 2007 study found that this activity was less likely to be carried out by those from an impoverished background. Examples of this activity include the Kunduz airlift in 2001, which was “state-sponsored” and led to a practitioner of this activity living in Abbottabad until 2011. For ten points, name this general term for intentional violence committed to achieve a political or ideological goal.",
      "answer": [
        "terrorism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. During this event, Captain Arthur Slatter helped kill a charging foe “just thirteen paces from where we stood.” This event was undertaken with hundreds of guides, including the leader’s son Kermit, and it provided the Smithsonian Institution with exhibits for its new Museum of Natural History. Eleven black rhinoceros, 17 lions, and thousands of birds were among the victims of, for ten points, what year-long expedition, begun in 1909 shortly after its leader declined to run for re-election, in which a former U.S. President shot and collected thousands of animals?",
      "answer": [
        "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt’s 1909-10 African safari",
        "any description of Roosevelt going on a hunt in Africa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Henry le Despenser ended this conflict with a victory at North Walsham. A leader of this event was slain while meeting with William Walworth at Smithfield. The Savoy Palace was burned down during this event, in which Simon Sudbury was killed after the cleric John Ball incited protesters to storm the Tower of London. This event was prompted by a poll tax of Richard II. Wat Tyler led, for ten points, what 1381 rebellion of the lower class in England?",
      "answer": [
        "Peasant’s Revolt or uprising, etc.",
        "Wat Tyler’s Rebellion, Revolt, etc. before his name is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this location, soapstone monoliths depict raptor-like “birds of heaven,” and houses in this site are made of mud bricks called daga. This city is legendarily conflated with the Palace of the Queen of Sheba. Decorative masonry used in a Conical Tower in this city lead to its Shona name meaning “houses of stone,” and parallel walls surrounding this city are known as the Great Enclosure. For ten points, name this “Great” city, built several centuries ago in Masvingo Province in its namesake African country.",
      "answer": "Great Zimbabwe"
    },
    {
      "question": "Louis-Antoine Beaunier received a royal commission to construct one of these structures to aid the mining industry in the Loire basin. The first of these structures in Paris started at the Gare du Nord. Saint-E´tienne was an early center for these structures, which were financed by the Perri`ere brothers through the Cr´edit Mobilier. In 1937, these systems were nationalized in France under the SNCF, which still runs them today. For ten points, name these structures, which link cities like Lyon and Paris.",
      "answer": "French railways"
    },
    {
      "question": "An observatory dedicated to this natural feature is located in the town of Parkfield. This feature meets the ocean at Mussel Rock. One event caused by this natural feature caused the collapse of the Nimitz Freeway and was broadcast live during the 1989 World Series. A disaster named for Loma Prieta was caused by, for ten points, what boundary between the Pacific and North American Plates whose movement also led to the 1906 San Francisco earthquake?",
      "answer": "San Andreas Fault"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Sanskrit word preta describes supernatural beings that underwent this process and became chronically hungry. Buddhist scholars have debated whether bardo takes place during this process, an idea recorded in the Tibetan Book of the Dead, since shortly after the death of the Buddha. A soul that has achieved moksha has been liberated from samsara, the eternal cycle of this process. For ten points, name this process that, in Jainism, Buddhism, and Hinduism, occurs after death.",
        "answer": [
          "reincarnation or rebirth",
          "transmigration of the soul",
          "punarjanman",
          "samsara before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term describes spiritual teachers in Jainism who have shown others how to achieve moksha and become freed of the cycle of reincarnation. Mahavira is the 24th of these figures.",
        "answer": "tirthankaras"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Near this city, Robert Abercromby led a counterattack and spiked a series of cannons, though that charge that was quickly defended. A siege of this city ended when Charles O’Hara presented his commander’s sword to Benjamin Lincoln, after Lincoln’s superior refused to accept the weapon. A popular account claims that an army leaving this city played the song “The World Turned Upside Down.” For ten points, name this Virginia city where Charles Cornwallis’s surrender marked the end of the Revolutionary War.",
        "answer": "Siege/Battle of Yorktown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This leader of the French Expeditionary Force marched with George Washington from Newport to Yorktown prior to the siege. At the surrender, this man was first offered the sword by O’Hara.",
        "answer": [
          "Jean-Baptiste Donatien de Vimeur, comte de Rochambeau",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man constructed, and named for himself, a fortified road along the Arabian border. The Edict on Maximum Prices was this ruler’s attempt to combat inflation by replacing the debased denarius. He appointed his valuable ally, the general Maximian, as co-ruler with Galerius and Chlorus as junior rulers. This man’s ascension ended the Crisis of the Third Century and, he ordered the last major persecution of Christians in his empire. For ten points, name this Roman Emperor whose tetrarchy split the empire into four sections.",
        "answer": "Diocletian or Diocles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Diocletian reduced the size of this bodyguard of Roman emperors, although he did keep their prefect as an important official in his empire. They were eventually abolished by Constantine.",
        "answer": "Praetorian Guard"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man secured backing in a “round robin” document after Cecil Morgan attempted to impeach him. This politician laid out his plans for a potential presidency in the book My First Days in the White House. This man used the motto “Every man a King” during the Great Depression, but he was assassinated by Carl Weiss outside the state Capitol building in 1935. For ten points, name this populist Louisiana governor, nicknamed the “Kingfish,” who promoted the “Share Our Wealth” program.",
        "answer": "Huey P. Long, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Long’s populist ideologies were shared by this “radio priest,” who Long considered as a running mate. This Catholic priest from Michigan turned on FDR in 1934 and spread anti-Semitic views on his radio show until it was forced off the air.",
        "answer": "Father Charles Coughlin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two answers required. A source of tension between these two countries was one’s use of the phrase “legitimate grievance” to describe the Chushi Gangdruk uprising in the other. These two countries fought a border war over the Ussuri River. One of these two countries provided half of the investment for the other’s first Five Year Plan. Richard Nixon visited one of these two countries in 1972 in part because of its rivalry with the other. For ten points, name these countries which “split” in the early 1960s, despite being the two largest Communist countries in the world.",
        "answer": "People’s Republic of China and the Soviet Union"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One cause of the Sino-Soviet split was Nikita Khrushchev’s Secret Speech “on [this concept] and its Consequences.” The speech blasted the propaganda and hero worship surrounding Joseph Stalin.",
        "answer": "Cult of Personality or Personality Cult"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Hercynian Forest stretched eastward from this river in antiquity, and the Ubii lived along its banks. A crisis was sparked in 1840 when Adolph Thiers proposed this river as a border. This river shares a delta with the Scheldt and Meuse that was the site of heavy damage in the 1953 North Sea flood. A legendary rock known as Lorelei overlooks, for ten points, what major Western European river that, like the Danube, formed much of the northern border of the Roman Empire?",
        "answer": "Rhine River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What city on the banks of the Rhine, founded by the Romans as the capital of Germania Inferior, is the fourth-largest in Germany and is home to a Gothic cathedral that was finally completed in 1880?",
        "answer": "Cologne or K¨oln"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the sixth edition of this work, its author added a new chapter to respond to the criticisms of George Jackson Mivart. Its author was motivated to publish following Alfred Russell Wallace’s paper containing similar ideas. This work doesn’t analyze the human race, which was later tackled by its author’s The Descent of Man. For ten points, name this book that introduced evolution by natural selection, the magnum opus of Charles Darwin.",
        "answer": "On the Origin of Species"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Advocates for Darwin’s work included this man, his “Bulldog,” who debated Samuel Wilberforce at Oxford in 1860. This man’s grandsons included Julian, an accomplished biologist in his own right.",
        "answer": "Thomas Henry Huxley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, a series of reforms of higher education proposed by Alain Devaquet was met with mass student protests. An infrastructure project in this country known as the Grand Projects sought to beautify its capital. During periods of cohabitation, a liberal leader of this country worked with E´douard Balladur and Jacques Chirac, a pair of Gaullist prime ministers. For ten points, name this country governed by Francois Mitterrand.",
        "answer": [
          "France",
          "the Fifth Republic"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Mitterrand’s tenure as President, he authorized the destruction of this Greenpeace ship, which was protesting French nuclear tests, by French special forces.",
        "answer": "Rainbow Warrior"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Kennedy Family",
      "prompt": "Which member of the Kennedy family...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Joined it by marrying Maria Shriver and was Governor of California after playing The Terminator?",
          "answer": "Arnold Schwarzenegger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was shot in Los Angeles by Sirhan Sirhan?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Francis Kennedy or Bobby Kennedy",
            "RFK"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Died after a long battle with brain cancer in August 2009, during his ninth term in the Senate?",
          "answer": "Edward Moore Kennedy or Teddy Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed in 1999 while piloting a plane to his cousin’s wedding on Martha’s Vineyard?",
          "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy Jr or JFK Jr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Re-married Aristotle Onassis after the death of her first husband?",
          "answer": [
            "Jacqueline Bouvier Kennedy Onassis",
            "Jackie O"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was hidden in a care center in Wisconsin after her father ordered her lobotomized?",
          "answer": "Rosemary Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed in an experimental Air Force mission over the River Blyth in World War II?",
          "answer": "Joseph Patrick Kennedy Jr. or Joe Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Married US Ambassador Sargent Shriver and helped start the Special Olympics?",
          "answer": "Eunice Kennedy Shriver"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The European Theater of World War II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country invaded on September 1, 1939, marking the beginning of World War II.",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that faced the Blitz and employed the Royal Air Force.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French line of fortifications that did not account for a blitzkrieg through the Ardennes.",
          "answer": "Maginot line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Desperate, late German offensive, also known as Operation Watch on the Rhine, that made a namesake shape in Allied lines.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Bulge"
        },
        {
          "question": "1940 evacuation of Allied troops by everything from naval vessels to fishing boats.",
          "answer": [
            "Dunkirk evacuation",
            "Operation Dynamo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed operation to “end the war by Christmas” that wanted to capture Nijmegan [ny-may-hen] Bridge.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Market Garden",
            "either",
            "both parts"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Operation, part of Bodyguard, that tricked the Germans into defending Norway and Pas de Calais, rather than Normandy.",
          "answer": "Operation Fortitude North and/or South"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of lower Normandy, where fierce fighting took place in Operations Charnwood and Perch.",
          "answer": "Caen"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century African Leaders",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Very non-African country, with capital Edinburgh north of England, “ruled” by “King” Idi Amin.",
          "answer": "Scotland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose independence was won by Jomo Kenyatta, who then led from Nairobi.",
          "answer": "Kenya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime dictator of Libya who was killed in 2011.",
          "answer": "Muammar al-Gaddafi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country founded by freed American slaves and once led by war criminal Charles Taylor.",
          "answer": "Liberia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country led by Emperor Haile Selassie, who defended it against Italy.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country, known as the colonial Gold Coast, whose independence was won by Kwame Nkrumah.",
          "answer": "Ghana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator of Congo who renamed his country Zaire and ruled until 1997, when he was overthrown by Laurent-D´esir´e Kabila.",
          "answer": "Mobutu Sese Seko Kuku Ngbendu Wa Za Banga or Joseph D´esir´e Mobutu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister executed in 1961 during the Congo Crisis, paving the way for the aforementioned dictator.",
          "answer": "Patrice Lumumba"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one role, this actor is shot many times before falling face-first onto a cake, walking into a bear trap, and falling off of a boat. This man, who played Officer Nordberg in the Naked Gun films, won the 1968 Heisman trophy while playing for (20 pts)",
        "USC and became the first player to rush for 2,000 yards in an NFL season. A In 1994, this man hired Robert Kardashian and Johnnie Cochran as (10 pts)",
        "defense attorneys. The book If I Did It was supposedly written by, for ten points, what running back who was acquitted of murdering Ron Goldman and his ex-wife, Nicole Brown?"
      ],
      "answer": "Orenthal James “OJ” Simpson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, one side’s failure to seize the Causeway Heights led to a prompt counterattack from James Scarlett in the South Valley. Colin Campbell’s 93rd Highlander regiment was dubbed the (20 pts)",
        "“Thin Red Line” for their resoluteness in this battle. Lord Raglan ordered the Earl of Cardigan’s cavalry to attack the wrong set of Russian batteries in this battle; that disaster was recounted in a (10 pts)",
        "poem by Alfred, Lord Tennyson. For ten points, name this battle, part of the Siege of Sevastopol during the Crimean War, which featured the Charge of the Light Brigade."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Balaclava"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Police banned this composer’s work after a demonstration followed a performance of his one-act opera Kaschchey the Deathless. The censors banned this man’s 1907 opera The Golden (20 pts)",
        "Cockerel for its implied criticism of Tsar Nicholas II. A suite by this man opens with the movement “The Sea and Sinbad’s Ship,” and his opera The Tale of Tsar Saltan includes an virtuosic excerpt that accompanies Prince Guidon’s transformation into an (10 pts)",
        "insect. For ten points, name this Russian composer of Scheherazade and “Flight of the Bumblebee.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As the leader of one governmental agency, this man claimed “whatever their politics, they shall be fed!” and refused to deny relief for the Soviet Union. This man and his wife would frequently converse in Mandarin to foil eavesdroppers, and this former (20 pts)",
        "engineer authored a widely read textbook on the Principles of Mining. This President reluctantly signed the Hawley-Smoot Tariff, (10 pts)",
        "worsening an economic disaster. For ten points, name this oft-maligned Republican President, the namesake of shantytowns during his time in office at the start of the Great Depression."
      ],
      "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An invasion of this country was justified through Article IV of the Treaty of Guarantee. Voters from this country repeatedly rejected the Annan Plans of reunification. Nikos Sampson was placed in power in this country by the EOKA attempting to fulfill the idea of (20 pts)",
        "enosis. Operation Attila was an attack on this country following the overthrow of Archbishop Makarios, and fighting in this country led to the creation of the (10 pts)",
        "Green Line and a UN buffer zone. For ten points, name this Mediterranean island country divided into zones dominated by Greek and Turkish partisans."
      ],
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Gustavus Fox’s attempt to relieve this location failed when the Powhatan was sent to Florida without his knowledge. Abner Doubleday ordered a cannon salvo on Cummings Point to defend this location. The unarmed (20 pts)",
        "Star of the West was sent to resupply this location but was promptly fired upon. PGT Beauregard’s bombardment of this location began when Robert Anderson’s (10 pts)",
        "Union troops refused to vacate their defenses in Charleston harbor. For ten points, name this South Carolina fort whose seizure in 1861 marked the beginning of the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Fort Sumter"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man claimed that using body doubles as a security measure was “movie magic, not reality” in a conversation with George Piro. Piro’s interrogation of this man, described as “High Value Detainee #1,” found he held (20 pts)",
        "no links with al-Qaeda or interest in creating an Islamic state. Nine months after a “shock and awe” campaign began, this man was discovered in a (10 pts)",
        "“spider hole” on a farm near Tikrit in December 2003. For ten points, name this Ba’ath Party leader who was hanged in December 2006 for crimes against humanity carried out as President of Iraq."
      ],
      "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A crime is committed on this holiday in the Hercule Poirot story “Murder in the Mews.” The namesake of this holiday is idolized as a distant ancestor of the central family of the novel Martin Chuzzlewit. (20 pts)",
        "Evey [ee-vee] Hammond is saved from assault on this holiday in a graphic novel by Alan Moore; a year later, she sets a subway train full of explosives to blow up a government building. The title character of (10 pts)",
        "V for Vendetta wears a mask representing the namesake of, for ten points, what British holiday, the subject of the rhyme “Remember, remember, the fifth of November?”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Guy Fawkes Day and/or Night",
        "the Fifth of November until read"
      ]
    }
  ]
}